So today's דף daf is ל"ז. Lamed Zayin. We are a little
behind still but, God willing, catch up. We pick up on ל"ו
עמוד ב', Lamed Vav Amud Bet, so the ל"ו-niks Lamed Vav here,
36, 36B, and the two dots about ten lines from the top.
We just had a very important discussion, שומר שמסר לשומר, shomer shemasar
l'shomer, is the act of giving it to somebody else to watch,
even
somebody paid more, paid less, with greater or lesser liability, is that
itself an act of פשיעה, pshia,
negligence? רב Rav said that it was not, and who was it
that said that it was? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said that it
was, even if you give it to a שומר חינם shomer chinam
who gives it to a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. The first reason
that the גמרא Gemara gives is because the person can claim, "I
never wanted anybody else to be handling or watching my object, I
don't care if he has a higher or lesser liability." And in
the end the גמרא Gemara rules here, right before the two dots,
that רבא Rava rules that you are חייב, chayav, it is פשיעה,
pshia, it is negligence, but for a different reason, because he could
say, "I've never trusted the other person to make an oath to
me." And as we're going to see in the גמרא, Gemara, that
could lead to maybe some different applications, different scope of when those
cases would be considered to be negligent. So now we pick up
with a related topic, about ten lines from the top, last word
on the line after the two dots, איתמר. itmar.
פשע בה ויצאה לאגם, pasha bo v'yatzah l'agam, somebody was negligent and
the animal went out into the swamp, ומתה כדרכה, umesah kidarka, and
it died of a heart attack. Okay.
So on the face of it, there's one question of is there
any causal relationship, or can there any causal relationship be sort of
even speculated to be present here?
So how much is the person liable for that initial act of
negligence? So אביי משמיה דרבה אמר, Abaye mishmei deRabbah amar, Abaye in
the name of Rabbah said, חייב, chayav, you have to pay even
if you're a שומר חינם, shomer chinam, even if you're a שומר
שכר, shomer sachar, because of that initial act of negligence of leaving
the door open.
רבא משמיה דרבה אמר, Rava mishmei deRabbah amar, and Rava says in
the name of Rabbah, פטור, patur, you're exempt.
Both in the name of the same person?
Yes, that's true, right, exactly. They're debating what their רבי, Rebbi, רבה,
Rabbah, said. אביי משמיה דרבה אמר חייב. Abaye mishmei deRabbah amar chayav.
כל דיינא דלא דיין הכי כהאי דינא לאו דיינא הוא, kol dayana
d'lo dayin hachi k'hai dina lav dayana hu, any judge who doesn't
judge this way doesn't deserve to be a judge. לאו דיינא הוא.
lav dayana hu. לא מיבעיא למאן דאמר תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס חייב,
lo mibaya l'man d'amar techilato bipshiah v'sofo b'ones chayav, it goes without
saying that the person normally says if you begin with negligence and
you end with an אונס, ones, with an unforeseen accident, you're liable,
דחייב, dechayav, so you're חייב, chayav, because that's what this is. It
starts with פשיעה pshia and it ends with אונס, ones, so certainly
you're חייב chayav here. אלא אפילו למאן דאמר פטור, ela afilu l'man
d'amar patur, even the one that normally says that when you begin
with פשיעה pshia and end with אונס ones you're exempt, הכא חייב,
hacha chayav, here you're חייב. chayav. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the
reason? דאמרינן הבלא דאגמא קטלה, de'amrinan havla d'agma katla,
because we say here that it actually is... כולא חד פשיעה היא,
kula chad pshia hi, to use a phrase used not in this
גמרא, Gemara, but anyway it's all one act of negligence. It's not
אונס ones at the end; this is part of that negligence. Maybe
the atmosphere in the swamp actually was what caused its death? We
don't know for sure, but it's possible and therefore we say that
this is all part of that initial פשיעה. pshia. So which raises
the question, well what do we mean by תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס?
techilato bipshiah v'sofo b'ones? Do we mean by תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס
techilato bipshiah v'sofo b'ones I was negligent and then, I don't know,
you gave an example before, it died of cancer, which was slowly
killing it, which clearly had nothing to do with my פשיעה? pshia?
Would you say I'm חייב chayav there as well? Do we say
the very act of negligence, even before anything happens to it, makes
me liable? I was negligent and now I owe the owner a
hundred dollars, let's say it was worth a hundred dollars. Okay, unless
somehow the animal is still around and then I can return it.
Okay, that's one way of understanding תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס, techilato bipshiah
v'sofo b'ones, that the act of פשיעה pshia itself creates that immediate
liability. That's not generally how it's understood. Normally the reason we would
say תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס חייב techilato bipshiah v'sofo b'ones chayav is
because we say that anything that happens afterward might somehow be related
to your initial negligence. And because it might be related to your
initial negligence, then you have it's like you have the burden of
proof to show that it's not about your original negligence. For instance,
so that's normal תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס. techilato bipshiah v'sofo b'ones. So
if it literally died of cancer after you let it walk out
the door, you would be exempt even according to that. What becomes
therefore what would we
see here, we're going to agree to that?
Pretty much because of the way the סוגיות sugyos work out. What
therefore is the issue of it dying in the swamp? So אביי
Abaye is saying, look, if you take the normal position חייב, chayav,
of course you can say, who knows, maybe it's related to it
being in the swamp. But even if you normally say פטור, patur,
okay,
this, אביי Abaye says, is clearly like it's a high likelihood that
it's the swamp contributed to its death. So in this case he
says,
normally תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס techilato bipshiah v'sofo b'ones is even if
there's some possibility that it's related you're חייב. chayav. That's the debate,
would we
say... Right, yes. תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס, T'chilato B'pshiya V'sofo B'ones, yes.
Relating to
the... to whatever factor, we would say תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס.
T'chilato B'pshiya
V'sofo B'ones.
Right,
so what תחילתו בפשיעה T'chilato B'pshiya does is it shifts the burden
of proof. According to the position... well, because the negligence is a,
you know, is basically like it's a fundamental violation of your responsibility
as a שומר, shomer, right? So because you basically, you know, you
know, sort of, you know, what is it, what's it called, a
shirking of duty... yeah, you... so therefore right, so now and you
are פושע poshea there's a presumption of liability until you can prove
otherwise. Now an interesting question would be let's say it's תחילתו בגניבה
ואבידה וסופו באונס, T'chilato B'gniva V'aveida V'sofo B'ones, okay, but we're not
going to... like because there's different degrees of negligence. But תחילתו בפשיעה
T'chilato B'pshiya is like a high degree of negligence, so the general
approach of חייב chayav is there's a presumption that you're to blame
for whatever
happens but as long as some argument can be made that it's
connected to what you did. So that's normal תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס
T'chilato B'pshiya V'sofo B'ones where it's debated: do you say חייב chayav
or פטור? patur? But Abaye says this case it's clearly, you know,
there's a high likelihood it's related to your initial פשיעה pshiya so
everybody would say חייב. chayav. Wait, let's just see what Rava says.
רבא משמיה דרבא אמר, Rava Mishmeih DeRabba Amar, Rava in the name
of Rabba says,
פטור. patur. You're... sorry,
חייב... chayav, where... yeah, פטור. patur, I just lost my place.
כל דיינא דלא דאין כי האי דינא לאו דיינא הוא. Kol Dayna
Delo Dayin Ki Hai Dina Lav Dayna Hu. And any judge who
doesn't judge like this judgment doesn't deserve to be a judge. You
gotta love it when it really gets like, yeah says you, yeah
okay. That's where you shouldn't be פוסק posek in this case. לא
מיבעיא למאן דאמר תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס פטור. Lo Mibaya L'man De'amar
T'chilato B'pshiya V'sofo B'ones Patur. It goes without saying that the one
who normally says if it begins with פשיעה pshiya and ends with
אונס ones you're exempt, פטור, patur. because that's what on the face
of it this is as a normal case of תחילתו בפשיעה. T'chilato
B'pshiya. אלא אפילו למאן דאמר חייב, Ella Afilu L'man De'amar Chayav, even
the one who normally says in such a case you're חייב, chayav.
הכא פטור. Hacha Patur. Here you're clearly פטור. patur. מאי טעמא? Mai
Ta'ama? מלאכא דמותא מה לי הכא מה לי התם. Malacha D'muta Mah
Li Hacha Mah Li Hatam. The angel of death will find the
animal wherever the animal is, meaning here it's completely unrelated to and
therefore has no connection. So if you sort of think about it
as an idea, right, so here's... I gotta cover these things or
they go back. So anyway, that's תחילתו בפשיעה... T'chilato B'pshiya... that's כולה
חד פשיעה היא. Kuleh chad pshiya hi. Okay. So here's פשיעה pshiya
and here's אונס. ones. Okay. So I'm negligent, I leave the door
open and it runs out and it gets lost. Okay. So if
the door... I leave the door open.
Okay. One scenario is it gets lost or it runs away. That's
like an immediate פשיעה. pshiya. Okay? Like that's really exactly what the
פשיעה pshiya leads to. Okay. The next possibility is I leave the
door open and what happens is it dies of cancer. Okay?
So there is no connection here, right? Completely unrelated. Okay. That's a
case that everybody would say is פטור. patur. It's not related at
all. Then you have a continuum of cases here about what happened
to it because the door was open, right? So and the normal
questions about תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס T'chilato B'pshiya V'sofo B'ones fall into
this continuum. Is the פשיעה, pshiya, is it possibly related to what
happened? When it's totally not you're פטור. patur. When it clearly is,
you left the door open and it ran away you're חייב. chayav.
What about the whole continuum of possibilities here of things which may
or may not have something to do with that initial פשיעה? pshiya?
Okay. So that's the question of תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס. T'chilato B'pshiya
V'sofo B'ones. Okay. So this is תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס T'chilato B'pshiya
V'sofo B'ones is when it might be related, might be connected. And
that's what's normally debated. So comes Abaye and Abaye says our case
of dying in the אגם agam is definitely on this side, it's
not even in the debated area. Okay? It definitely is related or
a high degree likelihood. Maybe he would say you sort of cut
the line there. It doesn't have to be 100% but a high
degree likelihood everybody would say you're חייב. chayav Rava says no our
case is totally unrelated, it's totally here.
And therefore everybody would agree you're פטור. patur. But the cases that
are debated are the gray area. And the question is what's gray.
Abaye says this isn't gray this is like totally black. Rava says
this isn't gray this is totally white. Okay, but the debates of
תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס T'chilato B'pshiya V'sofo B'ones are in the gray
zone. Yes.
So Rava would say that no matter where the animal
drops dead...
yeah, if it fell off a cliff because you left the door
open but the point is this is מתה כדרכה. Mesa K'darkah. This
just died of a heart attack. Right, so he says מתה כדרכה
Mesa K'darkah it'll happen wherever it's going to happen anywhere. Right.
But for instance if it got hit by a meteor though then
you could say well if
it had stayed at home it wouldn't have been hit by the
meteor. Exactly. Exactly. And that would be... Right, and now, yes, so
that would be exactly probably in this area where it wasn't like,
see what you said, the case is, it's actually the case of,
and I don't want to get into this too much, but the
case of let's say it did run away and it was hit
by lightning. So there's no question that if it was in my
house, it would not have been hit by lightning because my house
wasn't hit by lightning, and here it was. Okay, but does that
put it in this case or in this case? Because on the
one hand, was it causally related? Yes. But was it something that
could have been
anticipated at the outset that the פשיעה pshia would have led to
this? No. So that might still be in the gray zone, even
though in hindsight it was 100% causally related, we might not be
able to say that that was a total embedded in the initial
פשיעה. pshia. So that might be within this gray zone of תחילתו
בפשיעה וסופו באונס. tchilaso b'pshia v'sofo b'ones.
Rava says that this is not pushing animals off cliffs or striking
them with lightning.
Exactly.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says, is this not causally related
though? Right.
Rava is saying that it's totally in the uncausally related zone. Abaye
is saying it's totally in the causally related zone. But everybody agrees
when there's when there's a question about it, that's the debate of
תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס. tchilaso b'pshia v'sofo b'ones. Yes.
Justified by the extreme language here of הדר דינא הכי. hadar dina
hachi. Right, as if we're just talking about assessment.
Oh, that's an interesting point.
Oh, that's
interesting.
Crazy. It is an interesting point because normally in the ישיבה yeshiva
we hate to say that the אמוראים Amoraim are debating just how
to assess the facts because that's not an interesting debate. We like
to say that they're debating conceptually what are the parameters of the
דין. din. Although I have a friend, a colleague who's a legal
scholar who
says that
half the way law gets fought out in the court has to
do with the issue of assessing the facts, not about how you
conceptualize what the law is. And the גמרא Gemara tends to pretty
much ignore that. So you are right, we could read this debate
of Abaye and Rava to be a debate of defining what the
gray zone
means, but it sounds more that they're just debating how to assess
the facts. So it is interesting that in that context they're just
sort of saying, you have to be a judge if this is
the way you look at the facts, right? It's about an issue
of facts and not an issue about law, and it's about an
issue of a judgment call, so that's a good point.
Right, and you're saying also like what's the circumstance?
Yeah, but mostly it's about what's the law. All right, let's go
on.
All right, let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. ומודה אביי דהדרה לבי מרי ומתה
דפטור.
umodeh Abaye
d'hadrah l'bei marei umesa d'patur. But
Abaye would agree that if the animal went to the swamp and
came back home and it died, you would be exempt. Now why?
Maybe it took in some of that air of the swamp.
מאי טעמא דהדרה ליה mai ta'ama d'hadrah leh because it came back,
ולכא למימר הבלא דאגמא קטלה. v'leka l'meimar havla d'agma katlah. You can't
say the air of the swamp killed it. Which is bizarre
because maybe it did suck in some of that air of that
swamp. Which again raises questions of how much are we really asking
scientists and doing a scientific assessment or so on, or how much
is there some more degree of a formalism here? If it died
in the swamp and it was in the swamp because of your
negligence, we're going to attribute it to the swamp. If it died
in the home, then we're not. Meaning even if a scientist were
to tell us that actually there is maybe the possibility that some
of that air had something to do with it, it doesn't matter
somehow in the formal sense, it's back home and it died, and
therefore we're going to say it's not about your negligence. So again,
one wonders how much is there some formal parameters going here, how
much is it like a straight objective assessment. Okay.
And they may say, look, because in those days scientists couldn't do
an autopsy and think.
Right, but there's still an assertion הבלא דאגמא, havla d'agma, the air
of the swamp, so it's a little that's why the גמרא Gemara
has to point it out, that we're no longer concerned about the
air of the swamp. It could have spent three hours there and
come home and died, and oh okay, then you're פטור. patur To
be like wait, why isn't it based on the air of the
swamp? So it does seem like there's some sort of formal parameters
going on here as well. Okay. ומודה רבא כל היכא דאגנבה גנב
באגם ומתה כדרכה בי גנב דחייב. umodeh Rava kol heicha d'ignavah ganav
b'agam umesa kedarka bei ganav d'chayav.
Let's say a גנב ganav came and took it from the swamp,
then of course you'd be חייב chayav. because that would be a
case of like probably כולי עלמא פשיעה היא. kulei alma pshia hi.
Because it was outdoors, you're חייב.
chayav No, no, you the שומר.
shomer. You the שומר shomer are פושע, poshea, it runs to the
swamp and the גנב ganav takes it, okay, then you'd be חייב
chayav? to the owner and probably that would be everybody would agree,
even forget תחילתו בפשיעה. tchilaso b'pshia. The reason it got stolen was
it wasn't in your house, it was outdoors. The גנב ganav was
able to... No, no, you're שומר חנם. shomer chinam. But yeah, it's
considered פשיעה, pshia, it's not considered גניבה. gniva. The reason it was
stolen was because of your original negligence, it wasn't at home. Okay,
so that's maybe everybody would agree, even if you say תחילתו בפשיעה
וסופו באונס פטור, tchilaso b'pshia v'sofo b'ones patur, that's part of your
original negligence. But now Rava's חידוש chiddush is that even if now
it dies in the גנב's ganav house, why don't you say מלאך
המות מה לי הכא מה לי התם? malach ha-maves mah li hacha
mah li hasam? Okay, I'm פטור patur to the owner because it
died, it would have died anywhere. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי
טעמא, mai ta'ama, why there does he agree you're חייב? chayav? דאי
שבקה מלאך המות, d'ei shavkah malach ha-maves, if the angel of death
had left it... So the גמרא Gemara says מאי טעמא mai ta'ama
why there just this סיפא sefa make you חייב? chayav, דאישתכח d'ishta'ka
because מלאך המות malach hamavet if the angel of death had left
it, so בבי bevei the גנב ganav הוי קאימא, havei ka'ima, it
would still have been in the גנב'ס ganav's house. So you became
liable from the moment that it was stolen, okay? And that created
the liability. So we don't sort of say you get off the
hook now because it died and you're not liable for the death.
You're still liable for the fact that it was stolen, okay? And
therefore, which is an interesting question, right, because you could have said
like exactly that gets to the question of תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס.
techilato bifshia vesofo be'ones. At what stage do I owe the owner
the money, right? Is it at stage that I'm negligent and it
ran
away? Well, no, because I know where it is. Okay, when is
the animal considered to be damaged, destroyed? When does my monetary obligation
kick in, right? So you could make that was an argument to
say that as immediately as soon as I was negligent, but we
don't say that, okay? But here רבא Rava is saying, well, as
soon as it was stolen, then you become liable. And then even
if it dies, yeah, then you go and get back and reverse
it. And then even if it dies, it doesn't change your initial
liability. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay,
אמר ליה אביי לרבא. amar lei Abaye le'Rava. So אביי Abaye said
to רבא. Rava.
By the way, I got to say I do like something about
the idea of speaking about the angel of death and animals. It
says something about like animal life. You know, normally you think about
the angel of death for human beings, right? No, the angel of
death is concerned about animals too, okay? They're not inanimate objects. Okay,
אמר ליה אביי לרבא. amar lei Abaye le'Rava. אביי Abaye said to
רבא. Rava. לדידך דאמרת מלאך המות מה לי הכא מה לי התם.
ledidach de'amart malach hamavet mah li hacha mah li hatam. You, רבא,
Rava, you say wherever something dies we're going to assume it has
nothing to do with the place that it's at. What do I
care if it's there, if it's somewhere else? So האי דאותיב רבי
אבא בר ממל לרבי אמי ושני ליה בשנתנו לו בעלים רשות להשאיל.
hai de'otiv Rabbi Abba bar Memel le'Rabbi Ami v'shani lei b'shenatnu lo
be'alim reshut le'hash'il. Do you remember yesterday the question was if שומר
שמסר לשומר shomer she'masar le'shomer is חייב, chayav what's that whole debate
about רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, right? When I rent it from the
owner and I loan the animal to somebody else and it dies,
and the question is does the borrower, does the שואל sho'el pay
me rather than pay you, and I make money off of the
owner's animal? And the question was one minute, how am I פטור
to the owner? I borrowed something and then I lent it out.
That's like a שומר שמסר לשומר, shomer she'masar le'shomer, right? And so
that was the question if you remember yesterday. And the answer was
oh no, you had permission to lend it out. So he says
why do you have to give that answer? לימא ליה, leima lei,
why didn't you have a better answer according to you, רבא? Rava?
מלאך המות מה לי הכא מה לי התם. malach hamavet mah li
hacha mah li hatam. He should have said to him it doesn't
matter, it's true, the שוכר socher was negligent when he gave it
to the שואל, sho'el, but he's still not liable to the בעל
הבית ba'al habayit because at the end of the day the animal
died כדרכה kedarkah and therefore even though he was negligent by giving
it to the שואל, sho'el, there's still no liability to the original
owner when it was מתה כדרכה. metah kedarkah. Okay? So this is
like you could have given a better answer. According to you, the
case of the משנה Mishnah that a שוכר socher gives out to
a שומר, shomer, you could have said was even against the will
of the בעל הבית ba'al habayit and the שוכר socher is still
not liable because at the end of the day it died a
natural death. So that's his question. So אמר ליה, amar lei, he
said back to him, לדידי דאמינא אין רצוני שיהא פקדוני ביד אחר.
ledidi de'amina ein retzoni she'yehei pikdoni beyad acher. So now we're going
to circle back to the discussion that we had yesterday. According to
you, you said the problem, the reason a שומר shomer can't be
מסר לשומר masar le'shomer is because he can say, you know, I
didn't want my object to be in somebody else's hand. So in
that case, איכא לאוקמה להאי, ika l'okma l'hai, you had to deal
with that issue. How could the שוכר socher give it to the
שואל? sho'el? Why couldn't the בעל הבית ba'al habayit say, you know,
I don't want him to have it, that's an act of negligence?
And you gave whatever answer you gave. It wasn't the answer I
would have given. It's true, I would have said מלאך המות מה
לי הכא מה לי התם. malach hamavet mah li hacha mah li
hatam. But forget that it wasn't the answer I would have given,
it wasn't the question I would have asked. That whole discussion was
irrelevant to me. Why was that discussion irrelevant to me? Why aren't
you bothered by the problem of the שוכר socher that hands it
over to the שואל? sho'el? Because he says לדידי דאמינא את מהימנת
לי בשבועה האיך לא מהימן לי בשבועה. ledidi de'amina at meheimant li
bishvu'ah haich lo meheiman li bishvu'ah. Because I have a different reason
why I say שומר שמסר לשומר חייב. shomer she'masar le'shomer chayav. This
is what רבא Rava said at the end of yesterday. It's not
because I don't want the other person to hand my object. It's
because I never trusted the other person to make a שבועה. shvu'ah.
So in that case, the case of that the שוכר socher that
gives to a שואל sho'el and why wasn't that an act of
negligence is not a problem. Why is it not a problem? ליכא
לאוקמה כלל. leika l'okma klal. You can't ask it at all. Why?
Because remember what does the משנה Mishnah say in that case happened?
The animal died, the שואל sho'el pays me, and I take an
oath to the בעל הבית. ba'al habayit. Right? Remember the משנה Mishnah
yesterday? So רבא Rava says oh, so it means that the scenario
we're talking about is that the שוכר socher has first-hand knowledge about
what happened because he can take a שבועה shvu'ah to the בעל
הבית ba'al habayit that it was מתה, metah, that it died. Okay?
And he does take that שבועה shvu'ah to the בעל הבית. ba'al
habayit. So in that case, it's not a problem of שומר שמסר
לשומר חייב. shomer she'masar le'shomer chayav. שומר שמסר לשומר חייב shomer she'masar
le'shomer chayav says רבא Rava according to me was not the act
of giving it over to somebody else's control was an act of
negligence I don't want somebody to handle it, it was the original
owner's ability to claim I refuse to accept that other person's oath.
But that means that if you have a case of שומר שמסר
לשומר shomer she'masar le'shomer where you didn't have to accept the other
person's oath, one scenario would be that there are direct witnesses to
what happened, the other scenario is that the original שומר shomer saw
it and the original שומר shomer can take an oath. So in
a case where an oath can be given to the בעל הבית
ba'al habayit by the original שומר, shomer, you don't need to rely
on the second person's... Rav would say in that case there wouldn't
be a problem of שומר שמסר לשומר. shomer shemasar l'shomer. Meaning, you
probably shouldn't do it at the outset, but there would not be
a liability. The liability is rooted in the fact that the owner
can refuse the second person's oath. Okay, so that's so let's just
take a minute and appreciate that that's an important נפקא מינא, nafka
mina, right, you know, difference that comes out of the reasons why
שומר שמסר לשומר חייב. shomer shemasar l'shomer chayav. One is the very
act of handing it to somebody else who I never approved of,
and therefore there's no way out of that, that's a negligence, and
because that's negligence, then that's rooted in our discussion now, and then
if an אונס ones happens, it gets into this whole discussion of
תחלתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס. techilato bifshiya vesofo be'ones. But it starts with
the idea that handing it over is an act of negligence. Okay,
so Rava said, you know what, you're right, if you were bothered
about that, you could have given an answer that that was מלאך
המות מה לי הכא מה לי התם malach hamaves mah li hacha
mah li hasam and you would have gotten off the hook for
whatever reason, but that whole question wasn't an issue for me in
our משנה, mishna, because I don't think that handing over is an
act of negligence. I think the issue of שומר שמסר לשומר shomer
shemasar l'shomer is the owner's right to refuse the שבועה shevua of
the second person. And therefore, our משנה mishna is not a question
because our משנה mishna the first guy is the one who's still
giving the שבועה shevua to the owner, so there's no there's no
issue. Okay, so a nice נפקא מינא nafka mina between the two
approaches of שומר שמסר לשומר. shomer shemasar l'shomer. Let's continue now the
גמרא. Gemara. מתיבי רמי בר חמא. Metivei Rami Bar Chama. So we're
still going to deal with this issue about מלאך המות מה לי
הכא מה לי התם. malach hamaves mah li hacha mah li hasam.
So Rami Bar Chama asked, העלה לראשי צוקין ונפלה אין זה אונס.
he'ela lerashei tzukkin venafela ein zeh ones. If the שומר shomer brought
the animal to like the, you know, a clifftop, and it fell
off the cliff, that's not an אונס. ones. Oh, it fell off
the cliff. What the heck were you doing bringing it to the
top of the cliff? וחייב. vechayav. Okay, ומתה כדרכה. umeta kedarka. Right,
that's a ברייתא. beraita. Now the implication is, מתה כדרכה, meta kedarka,
if it died naturally, הרי זה אונס ופטור. harei zeh ones upatur.
It would be an אונס. ones. I brought it to the top
of the cliff, it only because it fell off the cliff. If
it had a heart attack there, I'd be exempt. ואמאי? ve'amai? But
according to you, Rava, why is that true? I mean, excuse me,
not according to Rava, according to you, Abaye, why is that true?
לימא ליה, leima lei,
why doesn't the owner say, אוירא דהר קטלה? avira deharka katlah? It
was the height of the mountain that killed it. You know, the
thinner air. If you're willing to say the swamp, you know, you
should say that. And notice by the way, it's not like Abaye's
going to take scientists to a swamp and to the top of
a mountain and assess. Right, there still is some formalisms to Abaye's
ruling. He says if it happens in a different place, I'm going
to assume that that other place contributed even to what looks like
to be a natural death. So the question is, if that's what
you're going to assume, that if it died at the top of
the mountain and you shouldn't be taking it to the top of
the mountain, because, you know, because you're being why are you being
negligent when you take it to the top of the mountain? Why
is taking the animal to the top of the mountain negligent? Because
it could fall off. So once you're negligent about the fact that
it could fall off, then it's then you should be liable even
if it died a natural death because we should assume the location
contributed to its death, just like the case of running to the
אגם. agam. What?
We do assume that.
Why are we because no, it says that you're חייב chayav? if
it fell off, which is the more extreme case, the more obvious
case. The implication clearly is that a natural death you'd be
exempt. Okay, so ואמאי לימא ליה אוירא דהר קטלה אינמי אוכצא דהר
קטלה. ve'amai leima lei avira deharka katlah inami uchtza deharka katlah. The
what's this אוכצא? uchtza? What? The tiredness. Right, right, the right, the
exertion of getting up the mountain. So how so, you know, you
Abaye, you have this presumption that it's somehow related if it's a
different location, so why don't we assume that here? הכא במאי עסקינן
שהעלה למרעה שמן וטוב. hacha bemai askinan shehe'ela lemira shemen vatov. There
was no negligence. Okay, the the good grazing area was at the
top of the mountain. So even though, even though it increases the
likelihood of its falling off, that's not an act of negligence because
that's the way, you know, shepherds, you know, that's acceptable norms for
shepherds. You take your animal where the good grazing area is, even
if there's somewhat of
a greater likelihood of
danger. Obviously it's all within the tolerable range. Okay, so that's why
there was no initial פשיעה. peshiya. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי
הכי, ei hachi, if that's true, נפלה נמי. nafela nami. So if
it fell off, why are you חייב? chayav If there was no
initial פשיעה, peshiya, there's also no negligence for it falling off the
cliff. So the גמרא Gemara says, שהיה לו לתקפה ולא תקפה. shehaya
lo letokfa velo tokfa. No, because you could have grabbed it. You
could have stopped it from falling. So the negligence is not that
you brought it there, the negligence is you should have stopped it
from falling, which is not פשט peshat in this ברייתא beraita at
all, but okay, in this or משנה mishna anyway. The גמרא Gemara
says,
אי הכי, ei hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, אימא רישא. eima reisha.
Let's look at the beginning. עלתה לראשי צוקין ונפלה הרי זה אונס.
alta lerashei tzukkin venafela harei zeh ones. If it went up on
its own, you didn't bring it up to the top, you know,
it sort of went up by itself and you were running after
it and it fell off, then you're an אונס ones and you're
exempt. So the גמרא Gemara says, you described the scenario now is
that had nothing to do with how it got there, it had
to do with your ability to catch it. So that should be
true whether it went up there, whether you took it there. The
גמרא Gemara says, איבעי ליה למתקפה. ibei lei lemitkfa. You should have
caught it in that case also. Because now you're saying it's not
about the negligence in bringing it up, it's about the negligence in
not catching it. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא צריכא שתקפתה ועלתה
תקפתה וירדה. lo tzricha shetakfata ve'alta takfata veyerada. No, no, no. The
point here is, is that in the first case, we're clearly dealing
with an animal that's out of... So that it went up to
the top, you didn't want it to go to the top, so
how did it get up to the top? Because you tried to
hold it back and it broke free of your control. So therefore,
that's an animal that you're not able to control. So the same
way it got up to the top out of your control, it
fell off out of your control, but you're an אונס. ones. You
tried to, but it broke free. Whereas in the second case, you're
in control, you're controlling the animal, you bring it up to the
top of the mountain. It is under your control, and you are
therefore being negligent when it slips off the mountain. So anyway, that's
certainly not פשט pshat here. פשט Pshat is that the issue is
the initial negligence, not the failing to catch it. But this is
a ברייתא braita that seems to prove against אביי, Abaye, that it's
only when it falls off the cliff, only when it's something that
clearly results from the initial negligence. Just being in a different place,
we're not going to attribute the natural death to the different place
that it's in as a result of your negligence. Okay, so we
have this very interesting debate of שומר שמסר לשומר, shomer shemasar lishomer,
two different reasons. We have the idea of תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס,
techilato bifshiya vesofo beones, where the issue is in this gray zone
where maybe it's related to your negligence, maybe it's not. And then
becomes the question of what presumptions do we make about certain cases
whether they may or may not be related to the negligence. Okay,
now we move back to the משנה. Mishnah. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar
Rabbi Yosi, כיצד הלה עושה סחורה בפרתו של חברו? Keitzad hala oseh
sechora beparato shel chaveiro? How does this guy make money off of
his friend's cow? Okay, which now again that's the case, that's the
case about I rent something from Jenna and then I lend it
to David there and therefore it dies. So David as a שואל
shoel to me pays me full, and me as a שוכר socher
to Jenna, I make a שבועה shvua and I make money off
the deal. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi is like morally offended. How
am I doing business with my friend's cow? So what do they
say? It's OPC, other people's cows.
Okay, so anyway,
you could understand רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi to be making a technical
legal claim, which is the שואל shoel is fundamentally, this real the
real title to this cow is owned by Jenna. And therefore the
שואל's shoel liability is really to Jenna, not to me, it's to
the original owner. Okay, you could say that. But that doesn't sound
to be what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi is saying. It sounds to
be more like a more like sort of moral principle. And so
let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with it. אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, הלכה כרבי יוסי. halacha kerabbi
Yosi. We rule like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi.
Okay, that yes, it's true, you do not pay the שוכר, socher,
you pay the original owner. אמר ליה רב שמואל בר יהודה לרב
יהודה, Amar lei Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda l'Rav Yehuda, so רב שמואל
בר יהודה Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda said to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
סבי, sabi, אמרת לן משמיה דשמואל, amart lan mishmeih deShmuel, you have
told us in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, חלוק היה רבי יוסי
אף בראשונה. chaluk haya Rabbi Yosi af berishona. רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi disagreed even with the first משנה Mishnah of our
פרק. perek. The first משנה Mishnah of our פרק perek is I
agree to pay the owner and then the גנב ganav is found,
I get to keep כפל. kefel. So he said, oh, רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi has a problem with that too. What's the problem with
that too? Why do you think רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi has a
problem with that?
Remember the first case? I paid the owner for the object that
was stolen and then the גנב ganav is found and I get
כפל. kefel. How is that similar to רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi objection
here? I'm also making money off of somebody else's cow. Okay, which
shows that רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi point is not a technical legal
point of is the שואל חייב shoel chayav to me or is
the שואל חייב shoel chayav to the original owner? That's one way
of understanding רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. At the end of the day
it's the owner's cow, so the שואל shoel is חייב to the
owner. No, his point is like a principle, it's a moral point,
it's a policy point. We cannot let, even if legally technically speaking
I deserve the compensation, I the שוכר, socher, we cannot let this
is not a tolerable situation to let me profit off of somebody
else's cow. So if that's true in this case, it's true in
the case of a כפל. kefel. Okay, yes, maybe I paid up
and maybe there is a good policy and societal reason to grease
the wheels
to encourage me to pay, but bottom line is we can't tolerate
a law that's going to let me profit off of somebody else's
cow, so we can't allow this to be the הלכה. halacha. Okay,
so let's take a look. So you've told us that he argues
even with the first case. הלכה כמותו או אין הלכה כמותו? Halacha
kemoto o ein halacha kemoto? Do we rule like him regarding our
first משנה Mishnah or not? Throw out the whole first משנה. Mishnah.
Okay, the בעלים bealim get the כפל. kefel. אמר ליה חלוק היה
רבי יוסי אף בראשונה והלכה כמותו אף בראשונה. Amar lei chaluk haya
Rabbi Yosi af berishona vehalacha kemoto af berishona. You're right, he debated
even the first משנה, Mishnah,
and we rule like him even in the first case. No כפל
kefel for the
שומר. shomer. Okay, the כפל's kefel going to go to the original
owners. איתמר נמי אמר רבי אלעזר חלוק היה רבי יוסי אף בראשונה
והלכה כמותו אף בראשונה. Itmar nami amar Rabbi Elazar chaluk haya Rabbi
Yosi af berishona vehalacha kemoto af berishona. So that's one set of
opinions. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, no, מודה היה רבי יוסי
בראשונה. modeh haya Rabbi Yosi berishona. Not only do we not rule
like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi in the first case, רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi himself never debated the first case. Why? שכבר שילם, shekvar shilem,
because he paid the owner. So in that case where he didn't
pay the owner, in our משנה, Mishnah, the owner gets nothing from
me and I get payments from the שואל. shoel. In the first
משנה, Mishnah, first of all, the owner isn't out anything, he does
get paid, I'm only getting כפל, kefel, but the owner is getting
paid. So A, it's not so unjust to the owner, and B,
there's a certain logic. If I paid the owner, I could be
now viewed as the new owner of the cow. And another way
to say this besides that logic is that this serves a larger
societal interest. It encourages me to pay, and therefore it is in
everybody's interest. So this is a very—there's a lot of different policy
and societal interest type—well, that's the same thing, whatever, policy considerations at
play in the first משנה mishna that aren't at play in the
second. And therefore, in the first משנה, mishna, even רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose says you get it, you paid, it's serving everybody a good
purpose, you paid and therefore you're seen as the owner, רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose would even agree in the first case. One minute. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar,
okay, שכבר שילם. shekvar shillem. שילם אם, לא שילם לא? Shillem im,
lo shillem lo? Wait wait, only if he actually paid? But רבי
חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi
Yochanan even, we said in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
לא שילם שילם ממש. lo shillem shillem mammash. You don't literally have
to pay in the first case. אלא כיון שאמר הריני משלם אף
על פי שלא שילם. Ella kivan she'amar hareni meshallem af al pi
she'lo shillem. As long as you promised to pay. So what, have
you switched gears now for the first משנה mishna to be relevant
to be the law to be active you have to actually pay?
All right all right we didn't mean it exactly. אימא מודה רבי
יוסי בראשונה שכבר אמר הריני משלם. Eima modeh Rabbi Yose b'rishona shekvar
amar hareni meshallem. We weren't being so technical there, technically accurate. What
we meant was רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose agrees in the first case
because he agreed to pay. All right certainly if he did pay,
by the way, which makes a lot more sense, right? Once you
did pay it's more easy to view the guy as the owner,
it is more understanding why he deserves to get כפל, kefel, he's
making things quick and easy. Right? Agreeing to pay maybe it's a
reason for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose to disagree in that case. It's
not as compelling of a reason. But in order to make רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan's statements consistent, we're saying no no no, in the
first case רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is prepared to go along with
it just because the guy promised to pay. That case at least
the owner's going to get his money, it serves a larger societal
interest. In that case we're okay giving the guy כפל, kefel, but
not in our משנה. mishna. Yes, Rabbi.
I just want to make sure this is like really basic. So
if the cow's worth $100, $300 is being paid out, right? The
100 to the owner to offset the cost of the cow, כפל
kefel 200, right? So $300 is being paid out.
Yeah, but the net is only—the net is only the—you know, the
גנב gannav is paying—the net is only $100 being lost by the
גנב. gannav. The owner gets his money back, I get the money
back that I gave the owner, and the net difference is that
$100 of the גנב—the gannav גנב gannav is out $100 and I
profit $100. Yes.
I think I know what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is really thinking
about and that is this idea of עושה שכר בפרתו של חברו
ose s'char b'parato shel chavero is—has profound implications in terms of you
know many aspects of the whole capitalist system, to things like what
do you do as a charitable institution when you get money from—that
turns out to be ill-gotten gains.
Well that's a little different, that's actually a בבא קמא Bava Kamma
discussion about taking צדקה tzedakah from the כיס של מוכסין kis shel
mochsin or whatever, but you know that's like—yeah, I mean I think
it does raise different issues, but you are right in terms of
the larger capitalist system, a lot of people have a lot of
good ways of being עושה שכר בפרתו של חברו, ose s'char b'parato
shel chavero, you know? You like take something for temporarily and then
you turn it over and whatever and you know it's using somebody
else's base property in order—I mean I don't know enough of that
field, but yes, I do assume that it's what?
Our whole system works like that. Yeah. Well look at travelers checks.
You give them the money today, when people used to use travelers.
Right. You give them the money today, you give these little pieces
of paper, your money's working for them. You may spend the paper,
you may not spend the paper, you spend it in drips and
drabs, but for a moment they're in your
suitcase, they've got your money working. Right.
The whole banking system is עושה שכר ose s'char with my money,
yeah that's true.
They buy your debt, they buy your accounts receivables. Now we're talking
about where this is—this is more like that. People buy your accounts
receivables, physical factoring.
Right right right right.
So then you get some percentage of your money immediately and they
work at collecting.
That's a good point, the whole banking system is being עושה שכר
בפרתו של חברו. ose s'char b'parato shel chavero. Yeah yeah yeah that's
a good point. You know but you could say but that's—but you
could say that's borrowing money. When I borrow $100 from you and
I invest and I'm being עושה שכר בפרתו של חברו. ose s'char
b'parato shel chavero. Yes, but
that's permissible. Right, exactly, right. That's really the difference on it because
the whole system of—you're right, obviously that's legal, that's borrowing money. I'm
allowed to borrow your money and invest it and make money. But
here the point was is that you were given it as a
פקדון, pikadon, you were not given it as a—to spend for yourself.
I didn't have the use of the $500.
This is the bank that handles the $500.
Yeah. All right. I'm not obligated to pay the owner the $100.
Right, what do you—yeah, what do you mean?
Only by paying him do I get the—oh in
the רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan case, right. I have the choice not
to pay. Right. Okay,
all right, you know what, let's fine, so let's to be continued
some other time offline. Let's take a look at the next משנה.
mishna. אמר לשנים, Amar lishnayim, okay, so we keep on going the
whole פרק perek here like the first פרק perek which is special
cases in מציעא metzia rather than God forbid we should start with
basic principles. Okay, so this is special cases in שומרים. shomrim. So
one case of שומרים shomrim is the guy getting כפל, kefel, the
שומר shomer who agreed to pay, the other case is about the
שומר shomer maybe making money off of it because he sublet it.
Now we're going to have a question about not knowing who to
return the object to. Okay, so let's take a look. אמר לשנים,
Amar lishnayim, says to two people, גזלתי לאחד מכם מנה ואיני יודע
איזה מכם. gazalti l'echad mikem maneh v'eini yodeia eizeh mikem.
I stole from one of you a hundred dollars, I don't know
which one.
Okay, או אביו של אחד מכם הפקיד לי מנה ואיני יודע איזה
הוא. O aviv she'echad mikem hifkid li maneh v'eini yodeia eizeh hu.
One of your fathers gave me a hundred dollars, I don't know
which one, and the reason by the way it says
fathers presumably is to make it that they're not coming with any
definite claim against me. They don't know. Okay, they're, I don't know,
thank you for admitting that, I don't know. I know I stole
from one of you, I don't know which one, they're not going
to be able to help me figure that out. They're not making
competing claims, they're not making any
claim. Okay, נותן לזה מנה ולזה מנה, Noten lazeh maneh v'lazeh maneh,
I pay each one of them of the full
amount, שהודה מפי עצמו, Shehoda mipi atzmo, because I owned up to
it myself, which is a little funny. Normally because I owned up
to it myself, like that should make me less liable to some
degree because it's all, it's all coming from me, you don't have
any claim against me. So just not to keep you sort of,
you know, in suspense, the גמרא Gemara basically says what that really
means is because I'm coming forward myself, it's clear I'm trying to
do the right thing, not just what is legally, you know, mandated.
If we were to tell me what are my technical legal obligations,
I don't care about ethics, just what's my technical legal obligation, well
technically you're exempt. Neither of them has a claim against you. You
don't know which one
you owe. המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi mechavero alav haraaya, you don't
have to pay either. But we're not saying it's them coming against
me and I want to know what are my rights, what are
my legal obligations. Okay, I actually come forward and proactively telling them
I might owe one of you money, I want to do the
right thing. You want to do the right thing? In this case,
give each of them a hundred dollars.
לצאת ידי שמים. Latzeit y'dei shamayim.
In other words, the whole assumption there is that you need some
incentive.
Yeah, that's an interesting question about how that might play. I don't
know... I don't know, it's a good point. Okay.
What's splitting and giving you each 50?
Yeah, but then, but then I won't have been יוצא ידי שמים
yotzei y'dei shamayim because I know that I would not have actually
made somebody whole. My goal is to make the person whole, right?
So the only way I'm going to do that is by paying
them each the full amount. שנים שהפקידו אצל אחד זה מנה וזה
מאתים. Shnayim shehifkidu eitzel echad zeh maneh v'zeh matayim.
Two people gave to a person to watch. So, you know, I
got money here from Jeff and from David. One of you gave
me a hundred dollars and one gave me $200. זה אומר שלי
מאתים וזה אומר שלי מאתים. Zeh omer sheli matayim v'zeh omer sheli
matayim. When it comes time to give you back what you gave
me, each one is claiming that they're the ones that gave the
$200. Now this is the opposite. This is you're coming with a
claim against me, I'm not coming forward, and the question is what's
my legal obligation to you? You might remember this from the first
פרק, Perek, this was referenced. Okay, in this case, נותן לזה מנה
ולזה מנה, noten lazeh maneh v'lazeh maneh, here I give what I
know minimally each one of you is entitled to. Each one of
you minimally is entitled to
a hundred
dollars. והשאר יהא מונח עד שיבא אליהו. V'hashaar yehei munach ad sheyavo
Eliyahu. Just, you know, keep that in escrow until Eliyahu Hanavi comes,
which is a way of saying like until any more evidence can
be brought, neither of them gets it. So it's in direct contrast,
right? Even though here you could say maybe in here like I'm
negligent, I should have been paying attention to who I got the
money from or whatever, but technically speaking, I'm
a מוחזק, muchzak, you're המוציא מחברו, hamotzi mechavero, right? There's, you know,
and therefore in terms of my... when I'm not coming to do
לצאת ידי שמים, latzeit y'dei shamayim, I just want to know what
my legal obligation is, the third hundred is kept in escrow. אמר
רבי יוסי אם כן מה הפסיד הרמאי Amar Rabbi Yosi im kein
mah hifsid haramai? Now the same Rabbi Yosi who before was complaining
how can this guy do business with his friend's cow and that's
probably part of the reason this is being brought in here, right,
Rabbi Yosi sort of raises these sort of like larger moral policy
considerations. It's all very nice technically speaking, you know, each one got
the money they definitely owed and the third hundred which is disputed
is put away. But that is not, that is going to be
a counter-incentive to people to be honest, because I can always just
go ahead and claim that 200 is mine, and I'm going to
get my hundred back minimally, and maybe the other guy in the
end, maybe he'll agree to say look what good is that third
hundred doing being kept in escrow, let's just split it, right? So
I don't wind up losing anything anyway. So there's no loss for
me to make, to lie. So technically this might be the right
legal answer but it's not the right societal answer because there's nothing
stopping the guy from being dishonest.
אלא הכל יהא מונח עד שיבא אליהו. Ela hakol yehei munach ad
sheyavo Eliyahu. Put all $300 in escrow. Okay, so therefore, now you
could still say maybe I don't need money as much as the
other guy, you know, I'm the רמאי ramai here, right? So fine,
let it all be in escrow. He's going to need the money,
he's going to want to make a deal with me anyway and
we'll split it. Maybe. But maybe I do need the money, and
maybe the fact that my money is going to be tied up
for an indefinite period of time is going to make me pause
for a moment before I lie and say that it's my $200.
Okay, so Rabbi Yosi has bigger societal fish to fry, alright, and
therefore he says put it all in escrow. וכן שני כלים, V'chen
shnei keilim, let's say there're two vessels. אחד יפה מנה ואחד יפה
אלף זוז. Echad yafeh maneh v'echad yafeh elef zuz. Okay, so one
person gives me to watch his, you know, his nice מנורה menorah
that he just bought at the store worth a hundred dollars and
the other gives me his antique מנורה menorah worth a thousand dollars.
זה אומר יפה שלי וזה אומר יפה שלי. Zeh omer yafeh sheli
v'zeh omer yafeh sheli. And then it came time to give it
back at חנוכה Chanukah and each one wants Back and each one
says that they have the nicer one. נותן את הקטן לאחד מהם,
noten et hakatan l'echad mehem, I give one of them the smaller
one, ומתוך הגדול נותן דמי קטן לשני, u'mitoch hagadol noten d'mei katan
l'sheni, and from the big one give the value of the smaller
one to the other, so it's just a similar פסק psak as
before, you know, give each one minimally what they're entitled to. But
what does this mean? I mean, you would think what it means
is, sell the thousand dollar menorah, give the guy a hundred dollars,
and put the nine hundred dollars in escrow. If you look at
רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says: מתוך הגדול, mitoch hagadol, see the last
רש"י Rashi on the משנה, mishnah, ישברנו, yeshabrenu, which is actually based
on the next, on the גמרא. Gemara. So what I do is
I take this gorgeous thousand dollar menorah and I break it in
half, you know, and I give him a little piece of the
silver menorah, here take that,
which is no longer worth a thousand dollars, the little piece he
gets isn't anyway. So we'll see about, it's a little crazy, we'll
see about that in the גמרא. Gemara. I'm not sure that's how
it, exactly, it's exactly, it's King שלמה, Shlomo, exactly. Anyway, והשאר יהא
מונח עד שיבא אליהו. v'hashar yehei munach ad she-yavo Eliyahu. אמר רבי
יוסי אם כן מה הפסיד הרמאי? Amar Rabbi Yosi im kein mah
hifsid ha-ramai? What is the רמאי ramai losing? And not only that,
like it's really particular in this case, because you're right, it is
like King שלמה. Shlomo. The guy whose real menorah it's going to
be like: "Ah! Don't do that!", you know. Let's just split it,
or something like that. Okay, we'll split the value. Okay. So Rabbi
Yosi says there is nothing stopping the רמאי ramai from doing this.
אלא הכל יהא מונח עד שיבא אליהו. Ella hakol yehei munach ad
she-yavo Eliyahu. So again, the reason presumably this is brought in is,
A, it has to do with cases of פיקדון pikadon and שומרים,
shomrim, but also B, it has to do with Rabbi Yosi raising
bigger policy considerations. Alright, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
אמר מר. Amar Mar. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara wants to understand
why when I come forward, I already gave you the answer, I'm
coming לצאת ידי שמים, latzet yedei shamayim, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't
realize that initially. Why when I come forward and I say I
don't know which one I stole from, I have to pay both
of you? אמר משום דמספקא אפקוני ממונא? Amar mishum d'mesapka apkonie mamona?
It seems like from a doubt we will extract money? ולא אמרינן
אוקי ממונא בחזקת מריה? Velo amrinan uki mamona b'chezkat marei? And we
don't say keep the money in the possession of the person who
is possessing it right now until somebody else can prove that it's
theirs? Right, which is against our general principle of המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה. hamotzi me-chavero alav ha-ra'ayah. ורמינהי, U'remi-nehu, I ask you on this:
שניים שהפקידו אצל אחד זה מנה וזה מאתיים. זה אומר שלי מאתיים
וזה אומר שלי מאתיים. נותן לזה מנה ולזה מנה והשאר יהא מונח
עד שיבא אליהו. shnayim she-hifkidu eitzel echad, zeh maneh v'zeh matayim. Zeh
omer sheli matayim v'zeh omer sheli matayim. Noten la-zeh maneh vela-zeh maneh,
v'hashar yehei munach ad she-yavo Eliyahu. The exact next statement in the
משנה. mishnah. The next statement in the משנה mishnah is that the
third hundred which is disputed, when one says two hundred, one says
a hundred, is you don't have to pay it out to both
people, you keep it in escrow. So why does the beginning of
the משנה mishnah say you pay each person, you know, the money
in doubt, and the second case of the משנה mishnah says you
hold the money in doubt in escrow? How do you explain the
two halves of the
משנה? mishnah? אמר ליה, Amar leih, he said back to him: פיקדון
אגזל קרמית? Pikadon a-gezel ka-ramit? You want to show a pro, you
want to sort of make a contradiction between a case of a
theft and a case of פיקדון? pikadon? So, what's the technical word
for פיקדון? pikadon? Let's see if I have it, a collateral,
no, not collateral. There's a different word for an object that's being
watched, a guarantee?
No, not a guarantee.
I'm asking you to watch an object for me. I don't know.
What do you call the object?
Yeah, I don't know. Okay, what does your English say? Does it
have something for פיקדון? pikadon?
Surety?
No, surety is a type of collateral.
Yeah, it just says appropriate property, bailment!
Bailment! Oh, that's the word, bailment. Bailee, that's the old Soncino words
which drove me crazy. But a שומר shomer is a bailee, and
a פיקדון pikadon is a bailment. Okay, I'm going to go with
פיקדון. pikadon. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so, so אמר
ליה פיקדון אגזל קרמית? so amar leih pikadon a-gezel ka-ramit? You want
to make a contradiction between a case of theft and a case
of פיקדון? pikadon? So גזל דעביד איסורא, gezel d'avid issura, in the
first case of the משנה mishnah I say I stole from one
of you. So I actually, you know, did a sin, I violated
a law. So that case קנסו רבנן, kansu rabanan, yes, technically I
should just keep the money in escrow, but because I stole it,
the Rabbis fined me and insisted that I pay each of you
full, we're assuming that this is a דין, din, not a לצאת
ידי שמים. latzet yedei shamayim.
Okay, קנסו רבנן. kansu rabanan. פיקדון דלא עביד איסורא, Pikadon d'la avid
issura, the case of פיקדון, pikadon, you entrusted it to me and
okay I forgot who gave what, but I didn't do a sin.
לא קנסו רבנן, Lo kansu rabanan, then we keep the disputed money
in escrow. So that's saying the difference between the first and the
second is the difference between גזל gezel and פיקדון. pikadon. The גמרא
Gemara doesn't like this. ורמי פיקדון אפיקדון ורמי גזל אגזל. U'rami pikadon
a-pikadon u'rami gezel a-gezel. No, no, no, these cases contradict themselves even
a פיקדון pikadon against a פיקדון pikadon case and a גזל gezel
to a גזל. gezel. פיקדון אפיקדון דקתני רישא, Pikadon a-pikadon diktani reisha,
because the, in the beginning of the משנה mishnah it wasn't just
a case of theft. The case of paying each person a hundred
dollars was also a פיקדון pikadon scenario. It said: או אביו של
אחד מכם הפקיד אצלי מנה, o aviv shel echad mikem hifkid etzli
maneh, the other case was I say one of your fathers left
a hundred dollars to me, entrusted it to me. ואיני יודע איזה,
איזהו, v'eini yodea eizeh, eizehu, and I don't know which one. נותן
לזה מנה ולזה מנה. noten la-zeh maneh vela-zeh maneh. So there you
see a case where it's just a פיקדון pikadon case, and rather
than saying hold it in escrow, I pay each one fully. ורמינהי,
U'reminehu, and I ask you on this: שניים שהפקידו, shnayim she-hifkidu, the
next case in the משנה mishnah where the third disputed hundred is
held in escrow. Why in the first case which is a פיקדון
pikadon I pay full, and the second case it's held in escrow?
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so before still we get to the answer
of לצאת ידי שמים, latzet yedei shamayim, we're going to try another
answer. רישא נעשה כמי שהפקידו לו בשני כריכות. Reisha na'aseh k'mi she-hifkidu
lo bi-shnei krichot.
In
the
first case, the רבא’s Rava gonna say the difference is: was I
negligent? Okay, now if I’m a גזלן, gazlan, I’m certainly negligent. Okay,
I shouldn’t be stealing. So if I can’t remember who I stole
from, my תקלה, takala, I gotta pay them both. Even in a
case of a פיקדון, pikadon, if I can’t remember who I owe
the money to, there are cases of negligence about that and there
are cases of not negligence about that. Okay, now, in the case
where I don’t know which of your fathers gave it to me,
רבא’s Rava gonna say there, I was negligent. I forgot. But in
the case about the 200 and the 100, I wasn’t negligent. Why?
Let’s take a look. רישא נעשה כמי שהפקידו לו בשני כריכות. Reisha
na’aseh k’mi shehifkidu lo bishnei krichot. It’s like people gave it in
two different bundles. Okay, why? Because
because here’s what he’s comparing. If you two come to me at
the same time, and one of you gives me 200 and one
gives me 100 and it’s all the same time, then it’s like
I’m not so negligent if I forgot which one gave it to
me. But if one of you came to me on on Monday,
and the other gave to me on Tuesday, that’s two כריכות, krichos,
two separate bundles, and I forget which one gave me the 200,
I am negligent. So in and if I am negligent, then I
actually have to pay you out both in full. So the רישא
reisha is one of your fathers gave me the money. There weren’t
two competing people and I forgot who was who. I only got
it from one guy. So the fact that I forgot which guy
I got it from, that’s negligence. That’s like you gave me each
of you gave me your thing on different days. And if I
can’t remember which guy I got it from, that was my negligence
and I have to pay out in full. So wait, let’s just
read it. רישא נעשה כמי שהפקידו לו בשני כריכות. Reisha na’aseh k’mi
shehifkidu lo bishnei krichot. Since there’s only one guy, it’s like two
different people on two different days. דהוי ליה למידק, Dehavei lei l’midak,
I should have paid attention who gave me the פיקדון. pikadon. And
if I forget, I’m negligent, and I have to pay each person
out in full. סיפא, Seifa, the second case, is נעשה כמי שהפקידו
לו בכרך אחד. na’aseh k’mi shehifkidu lo bikrach echad. They both came
together. He’s going to read that that was the case in the
משנה. mishna. It wasn’t clear. Okay, it’s as if they bundled all
the money together. דלא הוי ליה למידק, De’lo havei lei l’midak, and
the fact that I forgot which one gave the 200, which one
the 100, if you all came together and in presence of one
another, I have a right not pay so close attention. Why? כגון
דאפקידו תרוייהו בהדי הדדי. Kegon d’afkidu tarvaihu bahadi hadadi. So now he’s
saying, he’s limiting the case of the משנה mishna of the 200
and 100, it would be a scenario that they both came at
the same time and gave it to me at the same time,
בחד זימנא. b’chad zimna. דאמר להו, De’amar lehu, then then I’m entitled
to say to you guys who each one is claiming the 200,
אתו גופייכו לא קפדיתו אהדדי. attu gufaichu lo kapditu a’hadadi.
You yourselves weren’t suspect suspecting one another, right? You know, you know,
Eliyahu, you didn’t say, oh, I’m not gonna give this in front
of Jenna, she’s gonna see I’m giving the $200, next thing I
know she’s gonna claim that she gave the $200. The fact that
you came together and were willing to do it in front of
one another meant that you trusted each other.
So אנא קפידנא, ana kapidna, you didn’t care, I should care? So
basically what רבא Rava is saying is, the basic principle is: when
the fact that I can’t remember who I owe the money to
is due to my negligence, I have to pay out in full.
When it’s not due to my negligence, it’s המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה.
hamotzi mechavero alav hara’aya. So the רישא reisha where I forget who
I stole from or I forget who gave me the money and
there’s only one person, that’s my negligence, I pay out in full.
The סיפא seifa where it’s the same, we’re going to say the
scenario is the same time and not really being seen as being
so negligent here and it’s המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav
hara’aya. You had a question?
Would you say that this is another example of clarifying the facts
of the situation and then you extrapolate the principles that are going
to direct the law?
Yeah, I mean, every case has an abundance of facts but the
חידוש chidush of רבא Rava here, yes, every case is always—there’s always
an אוקימתא ukimta to try to explain what are the facts. But
the חידוש chidush here is the principle of if my not knowing
is due to my own fault, then I pay out in full.
Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: okay, so that’s
an okay answer so far in the משנה, mishna, but we’re not
done.
ורמינן גזל אגזל. V’raminan gezel a’gezel. But one minute, there’s still a
contradiction about two cases of theft. קתני הכא, Katani hacha, it was
taught here: האומר לשנים גזלתי לאחד מכם ואיני יודע מאיזה מכם או
אביך הפקיד לי מנה ואיני יודע איזה, ha’omer l’shnayim gazalti l’chad mikem
v’eini yodeia m’eizeh mikem o avich hipkid li man v’eini yodeia eizeh,
נותן לזה מנה ולזה מנה. notsen l’zeh man u’l’zeh man. When I
don’t know who I stole from, I give each person a hundred
dollars. ורמינן, U’raminan, I’ll ask on this: גזל אחד מחמשה, gezel echad
mechamesha, if I stole from
five
people—one of five people—ואיני יודע איזה מהן, v’eini yodeia eizeh mehen, זה
אומר אותי גזל וזה אומר אותי גזל. zeh omer oti gazal v’zeh
omer oti gazal. And here they’re actually coming with claims against me.
This one says you stole from me and this one says you
stole from me. So do I give each one a hundred? So
the answer is: מניח גזילה ביניהם ומסתלק, maniach g’zeila beineihem u’mistalek, I
put the hundred dollars between them and I leave. דברי רבי טרפון.
Divrei Rabbi Tarfon. So we’ll see about that in a moment in
the גמרא, Gemara, but the point still being, I don’t have to
pay them each a hundred dollars. And there, there should be more
of a reason because they’re each coming to me with a claim,
a definite claim against me. So אלמא מספיקא לא מפקינן ממונא, alma
misafika lo mafkinan mamona, even in a case of גזילה g’zeila from
one person and you don’t know, we don’t make you pay out.
So how do you reconcile that teaching of רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon
with our
משנה? mishna? וממאי דמתניתין דהכא רבי טרפון היא? U’miman d’matnizin d’hacha Rabbi
Tarfon hi? How do you know our משנה mishna is רבי טרפון?
Rabbi Tarfon? רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva there... disagrees. רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva
response to רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon is, אין זה דרך מוציאו מידי
עבירה, ain zeh derech motzio midei aveira, and that that doesn't get
you free from your גזילה gezeila and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
you pay each one the full amount. So maybe our משנה mishna
that says you pay everybody fully is just רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva?
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, דתניא עלה דהא, detanya ala deha,
מודי רבי טרפון באומר לשנים גזלתי לאחד מכם מנה ואיני יודע איזה
מכם שנותן לזה מנה ולזה מנה. modei Rabbi Tarfon b'omer lishnayim gazalti
l'echad mikem maneh v'eini yodeia eizeh mikem shenosein lazeh maneh v'lazeh maneh.
No, no, no, because רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon himself distinguishes between the
two cases. רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says when they're coming to me
and each one's claiming a hundred I put the hundred and I
walk away. When I come to them and I say, I don't
know which one I stole from, I pay each one in full.
So what's the difference? Within רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon really the question
is, why when I come forward and I'm being a good guy,
do I have to pay them in full and when they're coming
to me I can put the money in the middle and walk
away? So this gets to the core of what is the difference
of those two scenarios and finally we get to what the משנה's
mishna real point is. So the גמרא Gemara says, התם דקא תבעי
ליה
הכא בבא לצאת ידי שמים.
hatam dekatevai
lei hacha b'ba latzeit yidei shamayim. You're right. When they're coming against
me with a claim and the question is what is my legal
obligation? So since it's המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya,
I don't have a legal obligation. I put the money down and
I walk away. That's what רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says. But when
I come forward to them and the question is do I want
to do the right thing, then I have to pay them in
full.
Okay. דייקא נמי דקתני daika nami dekatania and you know what that
actually is in the text of our משנה. mishna. Because in our
משנה mishna it says why I pay them in full. It says
שהודה מפי עצמו. shehoda mipi atzmo. It says the reason I pay
them in full is because I'm admitting to it. So normally why
does admitting to it make more of a liability, especially if they're
not even making a claim against me? But it's because the point
of our משנה mishna is what to do to be לצאת ידי
שמים. latzeit yidei shamayim. שמע מינה. shma mina. That's a good point.
Let's just read one more line. אמר מר. amar mar. התם דקא
תבעי ליה. hatam dekatevai lei.
So they're coming against me with this claim in the case of
the five people. They're each saying I'm the one who stole from
them. והלה מה טוען. v'hala ma to'ein. What do I say in
response to that to them when each one is coming? רב יהודה
אמר רב הלס שותק. Rav Yehuda amar Rav halas shotek. I'm silent.
I don't know. Okay. ורב מנשיא אמר רב הלס צויח. v'Rav Menashya
amar Rav halas tzoveiach. No, no, no. I'm yelling and I'm saying,
no, it's not you. I didn't steal from you. I didn't steal
from you. I didn't steal from you. We're talking about the case
of רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. Five people come to me and each
one demands it. Okay. So what's the debate here? אבל שתיקה
כהודאה. aval shtika k'hoda'ah. The question is do we say silence is
like admission? So according to the second opinion, if five people come
and each one says I'm
the one who I stole from and I don't say no you're
not, then my silence to them is like I'm admitting and it's
like I admitted five times and even רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon would
say I would have to pay out to all of them. So
ומאן דאמר, u man d'amar, so what's the opposite argument? ומן דאמר
הלס שותק. u man d'amar halas shotek. So the one who says
no, no, no, we're even talking about that the guy is silent.
שתיקה דהכא לאו כהודאה היא. shtika dehacha lav k'hoda'ah hi. Sometimes silence
is admission, but here silence is not admission. מצי אמר ליה האי
דשתיקי דכל חד וחד. matzi amar lei hai deshtiki dechol chad v'chad.
The reason I was silent when each one of these five people
came to me with a claim דאמינא דילמא האי הוא. d'amina dilma
hai hu. It's not because I was admitting that he was the
guy, but because I didn't know. Maybe he was the guy? So
when he comes to me and says I'm the one you stole
a hundred dollars, I can't say no you're not. Maybe you were.
But I'm not saying yes you are. So שתיקה shtika in this
scenario is not an admission. It's an admission of the possibility. It's
not an admission of the fact that
actually I stole the money from you. Okay.
But שתיקה shtika doesn't indicate that he didn't steal from someone. Right.
And that's the case. I admit I stole from someone, which is
the logic question. If I admit I stole from someone, how could
I then deny when you come to me with a claim? So
yes I'm silent, but שתיקה shtika is not admission. It's admission of
the possibility. One more line here because I just have to do
this case about putting the money and walking away. Okay. אמר מר
מניח גזילה ביניהם ומסתלק. amar mar maniach gezeila beineihem umistalek. Put the
money and walk away. So the גמרא Gemara says ושקלו לה כולה.
v'shaklu lah kulah. What and then they're all going to take it
and fight it out? ואזלי. v'azli. And then they could just go
and that's it I'm done? והאמר רב אדא בר זבדא אמר רב
כל ספק הינוח לכתחילה לא יטול. v'ha'amar Rav Adda bar Zavda amar
Rav kol safek hinuach l'chat’chila lo yitol. Remember go back to our
אבידה aveida case. If there's an object that was left and maybe
it was intentionally left there. Okay. But maybe it was lost. Don't
pick it up because if it was intentionally left there you're taking
somebody's object and then they're not going to find it. Okay. ואם
נטל, v'im natal, but if I did pick it up, לא יחזיר.
lo yachzir. I don't return it. So רש״י Rashi says it means
I don't return it when somebody says it's mine because they don't
have a סימן. siman. But תוספות Tosafot says even better. It means
after I picked it up I can't go ahead and say oh
I shouldn't have picked it up and put it back. Because as
soon as I picked it up I become obligated to return it
to the rightful owner. Okay. And I don't satisfy my obligation by
putting it back and walking away. All right. So that's exactly this
case. You stole the money. You're obligated to return it to the
rightful owner. You can't put the money down in the middle and
walk away. Because rightful owner's not going to get it in that
case. Okay. So the same way in the case of the אבידה,
aveida, what do I do? I have to just hold on to
it until hopefully the owner eventually comes forward. Here too I should
hold on
to. But I can't just put it down and be done with
it. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב ספרא ויניח. Amar Rav
Safra v'yaniach. Yeah, when it says walk away, it doesn't mean let
them fight it. What it means by walk away, it means put
it in escrow and walk away, which is not exactly what it
sounds like, מניח אבידה ביניהם, meniach aveidah beineihem,
but anyway, but the גמרא Gemara is rightfully objecting, like that's crazy.
That's not the way to deal with it, right? And the ideal
way to deal with it is you put the money in escrow
and you wait till more evidence can come forward. So that's how
we're
like reframing רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. Yes.
Do you think there's like a difference between when it's two and
five? I feel like when it's five people it's like that.
Oh, everybody is taking an advantage of the opportunity. Could be, but
I think it's just more of a way of dramatically positioning רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, who says you have to pay each of all
five of them.
Okay, so to be continued tomorrow.
So ויניח v'yaniach as רב ספרא Rav Safra means like תשבי יחול
עד שיבוא אליהו.
Tishbi yachol ad
sheyavo Eliyahu. Exactly.
ויניח v'yaniach is like the technical word of ויניח v'yaniach in the
משנה. Mishna.